なんば　むった
かこく
くんれん
＜超過酷なサバイバル訓練中➡
As our brutal survival training continued,
Nitta revealed his phone was missing, and he was waiting for an important call from his little brother.
私は弟からの大事な電話を待つ
けいたい
にった
携帯を落としたという新田と➡
さばく
夜の砂漠を駆け戻った＞
So at night, the two of us backtracked through the desert.
I have to go back...
(新田)俺…戻るわ｡
(ケンジ)携帯？
Your phone?
(新田)とにかく みんなは
先へ進んでくれ｡
Anyway, you guys go ahead without me.
I'll find it and catch up before sunset.
日が沈む前に 俺は携帯を
探し出して すぐ後を追うから｡
きゃっか
その案は却下だ！
I can't let you do that.
We move together.
全員で 先へ進もう！
(新田)チクショー！何で
よりによって こんな日に➡
Damn...
Why did Nanba have to be the leader today?
南波がリーダーなんだよ｡
それで 今晩 その電話が
かかってくるんだよな？
So you're expecting a call tonight, right?
新田の携帯に｡
(新田)ああ｡だから
そう言ってんだろ｡
On your cell phone?
Yeah, that's what I've been saying!
だったら着信で
てんめつ
チカチカ点滅するはずだろ｡
Then your phone should start flashing when it rings.
It'll be easier to spot at night.
夜になってからの方が
見つけやすい｡
出発だ！
And we're off!
俺にも１人弟がいる｡➡
I also have a little brother.
今日 電話をかけてくるのが
その弟だ｡➡
He's supposed to call me today.
We haven't spoken in two years.
話すのは２年ぶりになる｡➡
ここまで来て 今さらなんだが
むだあし
無駄足になるかもしれないんだ｡
And I hate to say it after all our backtracking,
but we may be wasting our time.
多分 弟は
電話をかけてこねえと思う｡
My brother probably won't even call me.
That's how he is.
そういうヤツなんだ｡
携帯は光ってなくて➡
And if my phone isn't lighting up,
we may have already passed it.
すで
既に通り過ぎてるかもしれない｡
It'll be fine, Nitta.
大丈夫だよ 新田｡
携帯はあと４キロほど先だ｡
We probably won't reach it for another four kilometers.
昨日の食料のあったところ
多分あそこだ｡
It's probably near the place where yesterday's food was.
ちょっと待て！
何でそう思うんだよ？
Hold on...
What makes you think that?
Did you forget? About the snake?
忘れたのか？ヘビの時だ｡
走ろう南波！４キロならすぐだ！
Run, Nanba!
We'll make four kilometers in no time.
ええ!?走るの？
ちょっと待て 新田‼
Wait, we're running?
Hold on, Nitta...
Hey, Bro...
⦅ねえ お兄ちゃん
また山に 星 見に行こうよ⦆
Let's go stargazing on the mountain again.
What was it that you wished for?
《お前の願いって…
何だったんだ？》
Did you find it?
あったか？
(新田)ああ 光ってた｡➡
Yeah, it was flashing...
間違いなく弟だ｡
My brother called.
よかったじゃねえか｡
That's great news.
I missed another chance.
《俺はまた…のが
チャンスを逃したんだな》
着信 カズヤからなんだろ？
It was a call from Kazuya, right?
Yeah.
So I'm guessing you can't call him back?
やっぱ アレか？
こっちからかけ直しても…ダメか｡
(新田)それで電話に出るヤツなら
苦労はしねえんだけどな｡
If I could count on him to pick up,
this wouldn't be so hard.
もう弟は…かけてこねえと思う｡
I doubt
he'll call me back.
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#51 Living Stone
(新田)付き合わせて悪かった｡
みんなの所へ帰ろう｡
Sorry for dragging you out here.
Let's head back.
(新田)仲良し南波兄弟から見れば
あり得ないだろうな…｡➡
Given how close you brothers are,
this must seem absurd.
電話すら まともにできない
兄弟なんてな｡
We can't even talk over the phone...
理想だよ…俺にとって南波兄弟は｡
In my mind,
the Nanba brothers are perfect.
Let me just say that my relationship with Hibito isn't something you should envy.
言っとくが お前がうらやむほど
素敵な兄弟でもねえからな｡
ひびと
俺と日々人は｡
今でこそ仲のいい方だが
最悪の時期もあったよ｡
We get along now, more or less,
but there were some rough times.
We fought over the stupidest things...
くっだらねえ事で
ケンカになったりな｡
なぐ
一回だけ殴りあった事もある｡
Once, we got in an actual fistfight.
どっちかの舌打ちか何かが
引き金だ｡
It began over a tongue click or something.
殴ったのか？
ああ｡お互いな｡
You threw a punch?
Yeah, we both did.
日々人を殴った時…｡
When I punched Hibito,
I could feel his pain at the moment of contact.
日々人が受けた痛みが
手から伝わってきてさ｡
その後味悪い感触だけ覚えてるよ｡
しょうげき
殴られた衝撃は忘れたのに｡
And I can still remember that sensation.
I forgot what getting punched felt like, but...
それ以来 不思議と
ケンカしなくなったな｡
Since then, we haven't fought.
Maybe it's because we felt each other's pain.
お互いの痛みを知ったせいかね｡
I...
《俺は…➡
あの時 殴らなかった…》
I didn't punch him back...
Come on!
(カズヤ)⦅来いよ！⦆
Stop it, Kazuya... Let me go!
(新田)⦅やめろカズヤ！離せ！➡
お前なんてな
殴る価値もねえんだよ！⦆
You aren't worth punching!
《まるで テレビの中のヒーローが
悪役にでも言うような言葉を…➡
I responded like a TV hero,
talking down to a villain.
俺は自分の弟に…➡
To my own little brother.
殴るより…ひどい事をした…》
That was worse
than any punch.
(カズヤ)アメリカ…｡
America...
Revisit the Japanese Jupiter Observatory Project?
A message to everyone interested in space exploration and development.
From the five ASCANs currently in Houston.
Itou Serika
Kitamura Ena
Nanba Mutta
Nitta Reiji
Makabe Kenji
《メッセージ？》
A message?
優秀すぎる弟ってのも
悩みどころだぞ 新田｡
Having a super-talented little brother isn't so easy, Nitta...
I spent a lot of time wishing he didn't exist.
いなきゃいいのにって思う事
数知れずだよ｡
お互い様だから言わせてもらうぞ
新田｡
Since you told me how you feel, I'll do the same.
俺は…お前みたいな兄貴に
なりたかったんだ｡
I always wanted to be a big brother like you.
A big brother who could help
道に迷ってる弟を そんな風に
みちび
導いてやれるような兄貴に｡
to guide his lost little brother.
Nitta Reiji
[PC]みなさん こんにちは｡
れいじ
新田零次です｡
Hello, everyone.
I'm Nitta Reiji.
[PC]みなさんへのメッセージ…
そうですね あ～っと…｡
A message to everyone?
Right...
Uh...
After becoming ASCANs,
[PC]アスキャンになってから
僕らは➡
we visited facilities around Japan involved in space exploration.
日本中のいろんな宇宙関連施設を
回りました｡➡
We were inspired by the space fans who work there.
そこで働く宇宙好きの人たちに
刺激を受けたり➡
And next, we'll be living in Houston and Cape Canaveral.
今はヒューストンや
ケープ･カナベラルでの暮らし➡
じゅんかい
そしてこれから巡回する
世界中の宇宙センターなど➡
As we visit space centers around the globe,
僕の知っている世界は
どんどん広がっていってます｡
our world is opening up.
When I was young,
[PC]
昔の僕にとって 学校と塾と
家の中だけが世界の全てでした｡➡
my world was limited to school and cram school.
とても小さくて
狭いと感じていました｡➡
It was a small, cramped world.
だからかも知れません｡
なが
星空を飽きもせず眺めたり➡
Perhaps that's why I never grew tired of looking at the stars.
地球の外へ飛び出したいと
思ったり｡
Why I wanted to get off this planet.
If you're watching this,
[PC](新田)
もし これを見ている人の中に➡
今 自分の居場所が無いと
強く感じていて➡
feeling like there's nowhere you belong...
小さな世界に閉じこもってる人が
いたら聞いて下さい｡➡
That you're trapped in a small world...
Please hear me out.
それこそが
外に飛び出す原動力です｡
It's those feelings that drive us beyond our world.
(カズヤ)あ！また！うぉ～っ！
(新田)こりゃすげえな｡
Oh, another one!
This is incredible.
So many shooting stars!
(カズヤ)流れ星 流れ星！
ビュンビュン来んね！➡
They just keep coming!
おお～っ すっげ～！わ～っ‼➡
This is amazing...
ほらぁ！見に来てよかったでしょ
お兄ちゃん｡
See?
Aren't you glad you came, Bro?
まあな｡
I guess so.
願い かけ放題だよ！
You can wish as much as you want.
願いは１コだけにしとけ｡
でなきゃ叶わねえよ｡➡
Stick to a single wish.
Or else it won't come true.
なんたって あれの正体は
石コロなんだから｡
違う！ただの石コロじゃないよ！
After all, they're just stones.
You're wrong! Those are more than stones!
生きた石コロだよ！
They're living stones.
Huh?
すいせい
(カズヤ)だって 彗星から
飛び出してきてさ｡➡
You see, they break off of comets, at forty kilometers per second,
秒速４０キロで飛んできて
かがや
光り輝いて消えるんだよ｡ｶｯｺｲｲ！
before disappearing in a flash of light...
That's so cool!
生きた石コロって呼ぼう｡
これから｡
We should call them living stones.
現在
(新田)弟は将来➡
Back then,
I always thought my brother would find a job that would let him keep watching space...
なが
宇宙をずっと眺め続けるような
仕事をしてるに違いねえって➡
そう思ってたんだけどな
その頃は｡
生きた石コロねえ｡そんなに
宇宙好きなのか カズヤは｡
Living stones, huh?
Kazuya loves space that much?
Look, Nanba.
見ろ 南波｡
キャンプの火が見えてきた｡
We can see the campfire.
ああ｡やっと休めるな｡
Yeah, we can finally get some rest.
Hey, Nitta...
なあ 新田｡もしカズヤと
電話で話せてたら➡
What were you going to tell Kazuya on the phone?
何て言うつもりだったんだ？
わかんねえ…｡➡
No idea.
わかんねえけど そうだな…｡➡
No idea, but...
I guess...
弟も住めるようにヒューストンに
広い家を借りたんだ｡➡
I found a house in Houston big enough for both of us.
I thought maybe living in another country might help him.
ダメもとだが 異国の生活が➡
弟にいい影響を与えるかも
しれねえと思ってさ｡だから…➡
So I was going to invite him to visit, at least.
｢気が向いたら遊びに来い｣
くらいは言うつもりだった｡
《コノヤロー…最初は
嫌なヤツだと思っていたが➡
Damn, man!
I thought you were a jerk,
なんて弟思いなんだ｡➡
but you really care about your little brother.
なんかちょっと
理想の兄像として負けてる》
Am I about to lose my title of ideal big brother?
弟に一歩を踏み出す勇気ぐらい
持たせてやりたいって思う｡
I want to give my brother the courage to take the first step forward.
今の俺の願いつったら
それくらいのもんだ｡
Right now,
that's my only wish.
(ケンジ)お帰り～！２人とも｡
Welcome back, guys!
た～いま！
We're back!
＜私達 Ｅ班は この日 順位を
また最下位にまで落とした＞
That night, Team E was back in last place.
＜ペナルティは すでにケンジが
受けてくれていた＞
Kenji had already taken the penalty.
あやま
＜新田は みんなに謝り 自分の
弟の事を全て打ち明けた＞
Nitta apologized to everyone
and told them about his brother.
＜大した勇気だと思う｡➡
That was brave of him.
新田の弟が持つべき
勇気と同じくらいに＞
If only his brother were as brave.
じゃあ アマンティが
うらな
新田君を見た占い➡
Then when Amanti told Nitta's fortune,
やっぱり当たってたんだね｡
(せりか)あっホントだ｡
she was right.
Oh, that's true.
⦅弟さんが１人
いるんじゃないかしら？⦆
As well as one little brother.
⦅惜しいね 姉はいるよ｡ピッタリ
あんたの言う通りだ⦆
Close.
I have an older sister.
You got that part right.
⦅だけど…弟は いね～な⦆
But...
I don't have a little brother.
そんな事情があるとは知らずに
ごめんなさい レイジ｡
I didn't understand your situation.
I'm sorry.
いや 俺の方が悪かったよ｡
No, I should apologize.
《ああ…そうとも
わかっていたさ｡➡
Yeah, as I expected...
新田に弟がいると
明らかになった時点で➡
The moment Nitta said he had a little brother,
アマンティの占いは当たる！》
it was clear that Amanti's fortunes are accurate!
《つまり俺を見た時の➡
In other words, whatever upset her...
あのリアクションが
意味する出来事も！》
⦅あ…！⦆
⦅ん!?⦆
Y-Yes...
⦅そ…そうね…なんか
すごく…いい感じよ⦆
It will go very well...
《必ず訪れる！》
...will definitely happen!
《どんな悲劇が起きるか 見えて
るんだろ!?アマンティには！》
What disaster will befall me?!
Amanti's seen it!
ふぇ～！うう…｡
う～さび～！
Man, it's cold.
まさか こんな所で
見られるなんて｡
I didn't think I'd get to watch it from the middle of a desert...
(北村)早く見たい～｡
みんな まだ寝ないの？
I can't wait!
You guys aren't going to sleep?
何 言ってんですか 南波さん
今日ですよ 今日！
What are you talking about, Nanba?
It's today!
何が？
What is?
(新田母)カズヤ｡母さん
買い物に行って来るから｡
Kazuya, I'm going shopping.
(新田母)ねえ カズヤ 零ちゃんに
電話した？
Say, Kazuya...
Did you call Rei?
(新田母)《少しだけでも
話して欲しい》
I hope they can talk to each other.
[PC]⦅それこそが…⦆
It's those...
[PC](新田)⦅それこそが➡
It's those feelings
外に飛び出す➡
that drive us
原動力⦆
beyond our world.
[PC](新田)⦅大事なのは…動く事➡
It's important to act.
何もせずに止まっているのは
道端の石コロです｡➡
If you stand absolutely still,
you're only a rock on the roadside.
動いて動いて動く石は➡
When a stone is constantly moving,
流れ星➡
it becomes a shooting star...
生きた石コロです！⦆
A living stone!
そろそろ 空を見るといいよ
兄ちゃん｡
It's time to look up at the sky,
Bro.
Home
Sis (Cell)
あっ来ましたよ！ほら～｡
Oh! Here they come!
Look!
(ケンジ)え どこ？
Where?
わ～！ほら！
(ケンジ)あっ見えた｡
＜結局 このサバイバル訓練の
間は➡
Nitta wasn't able to talk to his brother during our survival training.
新田の弟からの電話は
なかった＞
＜それでも新田は一度だけでも
弟から着信があったって事を➡
But Nitta seemed pleased that his brother had tried to call.
何度も かみしめて
いるようだった＞
(新田)こりゃすげえ｡
This is amazing.
願い かけ放題だな｡
You can wish as much as you want.
＜おそらく新田は
この無数の流れ星に➡
There were more shooting stars than we could count...
１つだけ願いを
かけていた事だろう＞
But Nitta probably only had one wish.
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
＜３０人のアスキャンの中で
いち早く 宇宙に行けるかどうか＞
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#52 A Big Brother Is Always...
Thirty ASCANs are competing to reach space first.
And the survival training results will play a role.
＜それには このｻﾊﾞｲﾊﾞﾙ訓練の
結果が 関係してくるはずだ＞
＜夜が明けたら いよいよ最終日＞
Once dawn breaks, it'll be the last day.
＜けど 今は 少しくらい
星 見てたっていいよな＞
But for now, it can't hurt to watch the stars.
＜うわ～ 何!?何かいます＞
＜えっ!?＞
What? Something's there?
Huh?
＜せりかさんの見つけたものを
きっかけに➡
Serika's discovery reminds me of a time with Hibito from our childhood.
私は
日々人との少年時代を思い返す＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"A Big Brother Is Always..."
We're completely off the beaten path.
＜マジで来ちまったな
道なき道に＞
(南波日々人)パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
Please continue to support the JAXA astronauts.
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
すっげえ！
Awesome!